so in the first video which is gonna be
this one let's talk about the the niche
that has I think been produced by the
combination of the much longer than
normal power of the boomers and their
particular way of behavior basically in
particular their children Millennials so
a decent chunk and remember of course
reality is super complex and everything
is always much more complicated than any
given particular explanation could
possibly account for so this is just a
piece but it's an interesting piece um
so let's see one of the characteristics
that I think is really important
understand what's going on right now is
that Millennials have developed as a
group more or less obviously quite a lot
of diversity among whom Allah nails
aren't but more or less in a context
that has two or three primary
characteristics one characteristic is if
much higher than ordinary in human
experience level of the presence of
authority so this is the whole notion of
being raised in the context where
there's always some kind of authority
apparent around you no more playing by
yourself out in the wilderness always
some kind of playground coach five being
Sherpa back and forth in minivans to
play dates and things like that and by
the way more as time has worn on so this
is even even more true for the youngest
Millennials and probably even more true
for the oldest of Gen Z you know
certainly even more true the oldest to
Jen Z so I'm gonna call this a
infantilization this is a separation of
a relationship with reality physical
reality nature and to meaningful extent
also relationship with your peers
outside of a context of having a an
adult Authority in in in charge of the
environment
and this by the way was pretty famously
noticed for Millennials in the context
of I think was called helicopter
parenting where you had for the very
first time parents who would show up in
college context and university context
and have direct conversations with
college professors on behalf of their
college-age children and and and if that
seems ordinary to you I assure you up
until ten fifteen years ago it was
extraordinary it was been absurd for my
parents to show up at my university and
have a conversation on my behalf with
with a professor they may have had a
conversation with the professor to be
interested in what was going on but the
notion that they would come in and kind
of tell a professor to treat me
differently it is just almost amusing
and and yet I think that became at least
somewhat common and that's kind of the
point all right so the point here is
that that's the offensive
infantilization and I don't want him to
sort of denigrate the Millennials as a
consequence of using that term because I
think obviously by definition they were
the recipient and in many ways the
unwilling recipient of that so what
happens in that context and it's kind of
like two distinct things happen
simultaneously one is a real felt sense
sorry a real felt sense and also a
reality of disempowerment a lack of
agency a lack of real agency a lack of
capacity to influence reality directly
right in this context the way that you
influence reality is indirectly
influenced reality by influencing
Authority okay so you yourself don't
actually have direct agency in the world
what you have is the ability to cause
another agent and authority to behave in
a certain way so if you're if you're in
in nature like you're you're in the
forest you have to make a fire by
rubbing sticks together or whatever you
have direct agency the only way to solve
the problem is through your own personal
capacity to do stuff with your body in
your mind in the relationship is
something that does not care how you
feel or what you say but if there's an
adult there and you try and it doesn't
work and the way to get the fire to
start it
you figure out how to convince the adult
to do it for you now agency has shifted
the center of agency is in your capacity
to be affected at the levels of social
interaction and my proposition is that
this omnipresent or there's always the
thing that's present human field has
over the past twenty years or so in in
particularly in the developmental
environment of Millennials and Gen Z
really shifted in the direction of
agency as mediated is socially mediated
and then the next thing that happens is
you will adapt to that you know you will
optimize for your niche all right so
what has happened is that pseudo
intentionally okay I don't think
intentionally but there's a lot of
attention to it the boomers have created
a context which hasn't Fanta lized the
Millennials and have created a niche
where optimization for manipulating
boomer power structures has been the
primary mode for successful agency of a
huge cohort that Millennials not just I
don't mean everyone I don't even guess I
mean most but but the plurality at least
as a sensibility and those so this
explains a lot of what we're seeing now
and what we're seeing is a real felt
sense and a reality that agency is had
through utilizing techniques to convince
authorities to change their behavior and
by the way these techniques are
optimized to work on boomer authorities
okay well why is that as that last piece
so important well as Eric Weinstein and
many others have noticed the degree to
which and the duration over power in
social institutions maintained by
boomers is actually rather singular in
in history
so the boomer generation has had more
ubiquitous control over social
institutions of all kinds and over a
longer period of time than we've ever
seen before so it's a bit like a like a
monoculture for optimization so we've
got a situation where you have a
infantilizing instinct and
instinct to to provide a kind of control
structure to to wander how to be
involved in controlling what's happening
probably for the benefit intentionally
at least helicopter parenting I doubt it
is intended to be the child abuse which
has lasted a long time and being
ubiquitous which creates a certain tenor
or flavor or typology and and therefore
has been the the niche for optimization
and so Millennials at least within this
subset in this lens are optimized for
manipulating boomer power structures in
the social field if you use this to try
to make sense of what's going on right
now you'll see a lot of that you'll see
a lot of what's happening into the lens
of a body politic people and I'm
speaking mostly about the protesters who
have a distinct orientation that their
agency really is in manipulating
convincing power structures and the
techniques that they use are optimized
to manipulate and convince boomer power
structures which now our showing up is
being effectively controlled I said it
so it works the Millennials have figured
out how to manipulate and control boomer
power structures and so this is one of
the reasons why for example this fellow
sense of life there are no adults in the
room there are no adults in the room
right the kids are still kids they're
still not mature fully capable of taking
responsibility that frankly is beginning
to be theirs to take acting in a more
adolescent fashion because they are in
fact separated from agency and have been
separated from agency for effectively
their entire lives in a situation by the
way where they know things are up
and need to change and their tool has
been to modulate the behavior to
manipulate authorities now they're
really good at it and so the authorities
are basically just being a backward it's
kind of like the barbarians invading the
Roman Empire like the boomers capacity
to actually guide effective choice is
maybe nil I don't know but
it looks like it's there's either no
capacity or even negative it makes
things worse and the Millennials are
sort of rushing through the gap but
still in this mode of the way to behave
is to figure out how to get a thorn is
to to accede to your demands okay I
think that's the whole thing